<idea-plugin>
    <id>dev.periscope.phpstorm</id>
    <name>php-periscope</name>
    <vendor email="thamibn@live.co.za" url="https://periscope.thamibn.com">periscopephp</vendor>

    <description><![CDATA[
        <p>Live observability + time-travel debugger for Laravel. Pauses any request, shows every
        variable, SQL query, log line, dispatched job, fired event, cache hit, Redis command, and
        outbound HTTP call that occurred up to the paused line — and lets you scrub backward in time.</p>
        <p>Connects to <code>periscope-daemon</code> over DAP-stdio. Supports breakpoints,
        step over / into / out, <strong>step back</strong>, variables, watches, evaluate.</p>
    ]]></description>

    <change-notes><![CDATA[
        <h3>0.1.7</h3>
        <p>Six bugs found in a v0.1.6 audit, plus two features previously deferred to v0.2.</p>
        <ul>
            <li><b>Daemon-spawn errors now surface to the user</b> — pre-flight checks that <code>periscope-daemon</code> exists (absolute path or on PATH). Previously a missing or non-executable daemon caused the Debug window to open then close with no visible error (same silent-failure class as the v0.1.6 getState bug).</li>
            <li><b>Breakpoints set before the session starts are no longer dropped on first run</b> — the handler buffers registrations and flushes them after the DAP <code>initialized</code> event. Previously every pre-session breakpoint silently failed and had to be toggled off-on after the toolwindow opened.</li>
            <li><b>URL-encoded file paths now work</b> — breakpoints in project paths with spaces (<code>My%20Project/...</code>) no longer silently miss. The handler decodes via <code>VirtualFileManager.extractPath</code> with a manual <code>URLDecoder</code> fallback.</li>
            <li><b>Listen-mode WatchService no longer leaks</b> on session cancel — the per-attempt coroutine scope is parented to a project Disposable, so Stop / project-close tears down the inotify handle cleanly.</li>
            <li><b>DAP reader hardened</b> — case-insensitive <code>Content-Length</code> lookup per spec, safe cast on incoming messages (a non-JSON-object line on stdout no longer crashes the reader), and the reader catches <code>Throwable</code> rather than just <code>IOException</code> so <code>shutdownPending()</code> always runs.</li>
            <li><b>Step Back button no longer flickers grey on session open</b> — toolbar enable now uses a sticky <code>sessionInitialized</code> flag instead of <code>dap.isAlive</code> directly.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>New features:</p>
        <ul>
            <li><b>ConsoleView wiring</b> — PHP code output (echo, var_dump, etc.) reconstructed from the trace now appears in the Debug → Console panel with full ANSI / search / fold support. stderr-class output is rendered in red. Buffered before the platform requests the console so startup output isn't lost.</li>
            <li><b>Run-to-Position</b> (<code>Ctrl+Alt+F9</code>) — properly implemented via implicit continue-until-line on top of the existing trace replay. Previously fell back to Resume.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Settings editor migrated to the non-deprecated <code>addBrowseFolderListener(TextBrowseFolderListener(...))</code> API for forward compatibility past 2026.1.</p>
        <h3>0.1.6</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><b>Fix: clicking Debug with the Periscope config selected did nothing</b> — <code>PeriscopeRunConfiguration.getState()</code> returned null, which makes the IntelliJ platform silently abort the launch <em>before</em> <code>PeriscopeDebuggerRunner.execute()</code> is ever called. Now returns a no-op <code>RunProfileState</code> so the platform proceeds to invoke the runner.</li>
        </ul>
        <h3>0.1.5</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><b>Fix duplicate-scheme rejection</b> — when a Periscope run config already existed in <code>.idea/runConfigurations/Periscope.xml</code>, the platform silently rejected the auto-seeded one and the resulting "Switch to Periscope" balloon action did nothing. Now: skip seeding when an on-disk or in-memory Periscope config is detected, and resolve the live settings at click-time so the dropdown actually switches.</li>
            <li><b>Always show the "Switch to Periscope" balloon</b> on every project open when the dropdown isn't already on Periscope. Includes a "Don't show again" per-project opt-out.</li>
        </ul>
        <h3>0.1.4</h3>
        <ul>
            <li><b>Auto-listen on Debug</b> — pressing the Debug button with no trace yet now watches the trace directory and attaches the moment the next <code>.cptrace</code> lands. No tool window, no toggle. (Fixes #1)</li>
            <li><b>Auto-pick the latest trace</b> — leave Trace file blank to replay the newest trace in <code>/tmp/periscope</code>. Explicit paths still work for historical replay; missing paths surface a clear error within ~1s instead of hanging. (Fixes #2)</li>
            <li><b>Pre-filled config name</b> — new Periscope run configs default to "Periscope" instead of an empty Name field. (Fixes #3)</li>
            <li><b>Zero-config setup</b> — on first project open we silently seed a Periscope run config in <code>.idea/runConfigurations/</code> and nudge the user with a one-time balloon if they're currently on Xdebug/another config. Idempotent — does nothing on subsequent opens.</li>
            <li><b>Settings → Tools → Periscope</b> — application-level toggle to disable auto-seeding for power users.</li>
            <li><b>Suppress green Play button</b> for Periscope configs — only the Debug bug action is meaningful for trace replay.</li>
        </ul>
        <h3>0.1.0</h3>
        <ul>
            <li>Initial scaffold — registers the <code>periscope</code> debug type and Run/Debug configuration.</li>
        </ul>
    ]]></change-notes>

    <depends>com.intellij.modules.platform</depends>
    <depends>com.intellij.modules.xdebugger</depends>
    <depends>com.intellij.modules.lang</depends>
    <depends>com.jetbrains.php</depends>

    <extensions defaultExtensionNs="com.intellij">
        <configurationType
            implementation="dev.periscope.phpstorm.runconfig.PeriscopeRunConfigurationType"/>
        <programRunner
            implementation="dev.periscope.phpstorm.runconfig.PeriscopeDebuggerRunner"/>
        <notificationGroup id="Periscope" displayType="BALLOON"/>
        <postStartupActivity
            implementation="dev.periscope.phpstorm.runconfig.PeriscopeAutoConfigActivity"/>
        <applicationService
            serviceImplementation="dev.periscope.phpstorm.settings.PeriscopeApplicationSettings"/>
        <applicationConfigurable
            parentId="tools"
            id="dev.periscope.phpstorm.settings.PeriscopeConfigurable"
            displayName="Periscope"
            instance="dev.periscope.phpstorm.settings.PeriscopeConfigurable"/>
    </extensions>

    <actions>
        <!--
          Step Back slots in immediately after the standard Step Out button on
          PhpStorm's existing debug toolbar — sits in the natural step-*
          cluster instead of getting tacked on at the end. The action is
          enabled+visible ONLY while a periscope debug session is the active
          one; during a regular Xdebug session the button is hidden, so the
          toolbar matches PhpStorm's stock layout for Xdebug users.
        -->
        <action id="periscope.StepBack"
                class="dev.periscope.phpstorm.action.StepBackAction"
                text="Step Back"
                description="Move the trace cursor one step backward (periscope time-travel)"
                icon="AllIcons.Actions.Back">
            <add-to-group group-id="XDebugger.ToolWindow.TopToolbar"
                          anchor="after" relative-to-action="StepOut"/>
            <keyboard-shortcut keymap="$default" first-keystroke="control alt shift F7"/>
        </action>

        <!--
          Continue Backward is NOT added to the toolbar — it lives only as a
          keyboard shortcut + Run-menu item to keep the toolbar uncluttered.
          The user is one Ctrl+Alt+F9 away when they want it; toolbar real
          estate is reserved for actions used per-step.
        -->
        <action id="periscope.ReverseContinue"
                class="dev.periscope.phpstorm.action.ReverseContinueAction"
                text="Continue Backward"
                description="Continue replay in reverse until the previous breakpoint (periscope time-travel)"
                icon="AllIcons.Actions.Rewind">
            <add-to-group group-id="RunMenu" anchor="last"/>
            <keyboard-shortcut keymap="$default" first-keystroke="control alt F9"/>
        </action>
    </actions>
</idea-plugin>
